Guide to James Healy's The literary renaissance and politics of Ireland: ephemera, ca. 1890-1975
Department of Special Collections
Healy, James Augustine, 1891-1955, collector. The literary renaissance and politics of Ireland: ephemera,
ca. 1890-1975
M1138
Healy, James Augustine, 1891-1955, collector.
2.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Correspondence relating to the building of his book and manuscript collection, subject files, articles, publications, photographs, etc.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Gift of James A. Healy in memory of his wife Josephine, 1975.
Biography
James Augustine Healy was a stockbroker and bibliophile who collected books, letters and manuscripts in the area of Irish literature and politics. He collected from the 1930s until the time of his death in 1975.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
Correspondence relating to the building of his book and manuscript collection, subject files, articles, publications, photographs, etc.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Book collecting.; English literature--Irish authors.; Irish literature--20th century.; Ireland--History--20th century.; Ireland--Intellectual life.; Ireland--Politics and government--20th century.; Authors, Irish--19th century.; Authors, Irish--20th century.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Letters and Manuscripts
  - Letter laid in Peter Golden's The Voice of Ireland, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter laid in Eire Today edited by Henry Coleman1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters & Article laid in F.P. Crozier's Ireland For Ever 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Censored Letter Cover to F.A. King at the Literary Digest[1942?] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Evans Horrock, Liam Dunn, & James Healy1939 - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter laid in Arnold Sidney's Irish Literature and Its Influence. A Lecture. 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Shakespeare Festival Letters1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Article from the Irish Press and manuscript concerning Jacqueline Kennedy1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photocopy of ALS from Seaumus O'Kelly to Ernest Boyd1915 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters from Eduard L.Smith of Dutton & Co., & John Jerome Rooney1938 & 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letter from Isaac Butt to "My Dear Alderman"[1938] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter from Alan Michael Buck to Mr. James Healyn.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letter from Alan M. Buck to Mr. J. Healy1945 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letter from F.H. Boland (Rep. To U.N.) to James Healy1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letter from James Healy to Mrs. Ala Story1943 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series 2. Monographs
  - A Russian Honeymoon (A Play) by Eugene Scribe1890 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Babelot (Printed for Thomas B. Mosher)1903 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Salute to Roger Casement" from Wolfe tone Annual1959 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Souvenir of the Golden Jubilee of Fianna Elreann ed. By Cathal O'Shannon 1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "The Arbitration Treaties" (Speech by James A. Hamill of N.J. House of Rep.) 1911 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Kuno Meyer. "Message to the Irish People" during WWIn.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Constance de Markievicz. "What Irish Republicans Stand For" n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Report of Envoy to I.R.B." by William Crossann.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "The Foundation of the Republic of Ireland - in the Vote of the People!" by Eamon de Valera1918 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Memorandum to U.S. Secretary of State" from Patrick McCartan1918 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - The Re-Conquest of America, by A. Gordon Brown[1919] (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "A Summons to Service - From the Women and Children of Ireland" Amer. Comm. For Relief in Ireland[1920] (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Two Patriot Priests of Ireland, 1916-1925"nd (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Various Articles by Oliver St. John Gogarty1936 - 1940 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "What the Irish Did With the Puritans" by Benedict Fitzgerald1940 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "Hands Off Ireland" lecture by Liam O'Flaherty1941 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "Leabra arna b'Foillsiu" Celtic book list?1945 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Activities of the Advisory Comm. On Cultural Relations1950 - 1951 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Sir Horace Plunkett Centenary Handbook1954 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "Friends of the Library of Trinity College" Annual Bulletins 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Proposal - New Theatre for the Lyric Players of Belfast1951-1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Occasional Papers" - Cornell University Library Associates re Healy Collection, p. 171961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Houses of the Oireachtas - Joint Sitting" (Visit of President J. F. Kennedy) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Poetry Ireland #5 ed. John Jordan (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - American Book Collector vol.XV no.10 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "A Summons to Service" (extra copies) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dolmen Press Books (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cuala Press book announcement (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Irish Craftmanship" (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "The Language of the Outlaw" (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Larkin's Scathing Indictment of Dublin Sweatersn.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series 3. Subject Files
  - List re American Irish FEIS Instituten.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Report from American Committee for Irish Studies1974 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - 8 illustrations for the "The Lily Field"n.d. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Lawrence, T.E. - Auction matters1940 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "A Portfolio of Designs forElectra" by James Reynolds n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Felton-Healy, Tile portrait of W.B. Yeatsn.d. (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Series 4. Journal articles
  - General Cluseret. "My Connection with Fenianism" Fraser's Magazine vol.VI no.31n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Poets and Poetry of Young Ireland," North British Review1861 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Dowden, Edward. "Dublin City." The Century Magazine1884 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - MacDonagh, Michael. "In the Bye ways of Rural Ireland"1900 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - McGill, Anna Blanche. "Concerning a Few Anglo-Celtic Poets." Catholic World1902 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Of Lionel Johnson." Atlantic Monthly1902 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Blunt, Wilfred Scawen. "The Great Irish Epic"1902 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Gwynn, Stephen. "A Century of Irish Humor" Celtic Review1902 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 5 Articles by Fiona MacLeod in Fortnightly Review1902-1905 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Moore, Paul. "The Epic of Ireland"1904 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Scudder, Vida. "The Irish Literary Drama"1905 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - McCarter, Henry. "Scenes from the Early History of Ireland." Scribner's. 1906 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Ford, Mary. "Is the Celtic Revival Really Irish?" Celtic Review1906 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore. "The Ancient Irish Sagas" The Century Magazine1907 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Weygandt, Cornelius. "Literary Workers in Ireland Today"1907 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Gwynn, Stephen. "The Celtic Revival." Celtic Review1907 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Hyde, Douglas. "The New National University in Ireland..." Celtic Review1909 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - E.M.D. "The Writings of Mr. W.B. Yeats" Fortnightly Review1909 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "Some Writers of the Celtic Renaissance"1911 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Tennyson, Charles. "Irish Plays and Playwrights"1911 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Hoare, John Edward. "Ireland's National Drama." Celtic Review (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Graves, Archibald. "Celtic Nature Poetry" Celtic Review1912 Mar. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Hamilton, Clayton. "The Irish National Theatre" Celtic Review1912 Jan. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "The Celtic Nationality of Ireland"1913 Oct. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Ervine, St. John. "The Irish Dramatist and the Irish People." Celtic Review1914 Jun. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Index to Journal of American Irish Historical Society vol.XVI1918 Jan. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Newsletter of the Irish National Bureau no.111919 Sept. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Newsletter of the Irish National Bureau no.281920 Jan. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Newsletter Vol.II, no.311921 Jan. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Toksvia, Signe. "A Visit to Lady Gregory"1921 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Yeats, W.B. "Talk and Talkers" North American Review1921 Apr. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Various Volumes of The London Mercury (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Malone, Andrew. "The Plays of Lady Gregory"1925 Apr. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Celtic Digest1938 Oct. - Nov. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Howe, Joseph. "W.B. Yeats." Journal of English and German Philosophy1943 Oct. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Review of "W.B. Yeats by Joseph Howe" by Kathleen Coyle in Tomorrow1943 May (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Northwestern Univ. The Reviewing Stand1944 Apr. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Articles about Jim Connolly1952 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Address by John F. Kennedy1963 June 28 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Eire/Ireland" Bulletin of Dept. of External Affairs1955 - 1956 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - The Dubliner no.11961 Nov. - Dec. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Bulletin of the Eire Society of Boston vol. 22, No. 4-61964 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "That Old Triangle - A Memory of Brendan Behan" in The Holling Critic vol. II no. 11965 Feb. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - The Holy Cross Alumnus vol. XL no. 11965 Aug. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - The Holling Critic vol. III no. 21966 Apr. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - The Critic 1965 Dec. - 1966 Jan (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - The Shakespeare Oxford Society Newsletter1976 - 1977 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - The Passing Show (Newsletter of the Shubert Archive) vol. 1 No. 11977 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - The Passing Show (Newsletter of the Shubert Archive) vol. 1 no. 11977 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - The Society for Theatre Research Bulletin no. 51977 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - News Front (article about James Joyce)1967 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - "Irish Folklore" by G.M. O'Reillyn.d. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - "The Neo-Celtic Drama in America" by Lawrence Gilmann.d. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - "The Play that Never Was" (an article in The Irish Times) 1966 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Clippings and Reviews of Joseph Hone's biography of W.B. Yeatsn.d. (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Misc. Articlesn.d. (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Series 5. Programs
  - The Playbill for "The Playboy of the Western World" by J.M. Synge1937 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Invitation to Dinner Honoring Paul Vincent Carrol and Dudley Diggsn.d. (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Irish Arts and Artistsn.d. (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Ambassador Theatre Playbill for "Juno and the Paycock" by Sean O'Casey1937 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Program for Oliver St. John Gogarty Photographs (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Series 6. Photographs
  - Miscellaneous Photographs1952 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - One Postcardn.d. (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Series 7. Clippings
  - A: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - B: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - C: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - D: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - E: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - F: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - G: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - H: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - I: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - J: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - K: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - L: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - M: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - N: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - O: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - P: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Q: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - R: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - S: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - T: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - U: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - V: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - W: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - X: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Y: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Z: Miscellaneous, newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - More Misc. (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Series 8. Oversize
  - A Broadsheet no. 13-241903 Jan. - Dec. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Limelight edited by James B. Conolly vol.1 no.101934 Feb 7 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "Irish Speech Helps Production of Abbey Theatre"1938 May 8 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Leader vol.XCI no.19-21 & vol. XVIV, no.221945 & 1949 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Eire-Ireland no. 209, 280, 4411953 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Booklet Outlining a Literature Course1955 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Photocopy of Partial Script for "A Portrait of Oliver Gogarty"1961 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Masters no.40 (Jack Yeats)1966 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Eire/Ireland no.625 (President Kennedy Visits Ireland) 1963 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Eire/Ireland no.674 (Death of Sean O'Casey)1964 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Eire/Ireland no.706 (W.B. Yeats Centenary)1965 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The American Irish Historical Society1938 & 1967 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Exhibition Catalog for Oliver Gogarty and W.B. Yeats Collection in the Ellen Clarke Bucknell Library1968 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Articles and Letters (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Assorted Photocopies and Newspaper Clippings (Box 5, Folder 15)
Related Collections
Healy, James A. (James Augustine), d.1975.
James A. Healy Collection of Irish literature, 1870-1976 M0273
An online guide to James A. Healy Collection of Irish Literature is available as an XML document at: http://www-sul.stanford.edu/depts/spc/xml/m0273.xml and as an HTML document at: http://www.oac.cdlib.org/dynaweb/ead/stanford/mss/m0273/